All righty. בוקר טוב *Boker tov*. Today's דף daf *daf* is ס"ח
*samech chet* and we pick up with the משנה mishnah, *Mishnah* at
the bottom of ס"ד עמוד ב' *samech daled amud bet*. And the
last few משניות mishnayot *Mishnayot* other than the very last one which
we'll get to tomorrow are not really connected to נזיר Nazir *Nazir*
but they are sort of picking up on some loose associations with
the first opening משנה mishnah *Mishnah* about the principle of טומאת התהום
tumat ha-tehom, *tumat hatehom* and some lines that were used. So let's
take a look at this משנה mishnah *Mishnah*. המוצא מת meit, *Hamotzei
meit*, now we actually had an opportunity to quote this before when
we were dealing with issues about מת מצוה meit mitzvah. *meis mitzvah*.
המוצא מת meit תחלה *Hamotzei meit techila*, if somebody finds a dead
body initially, meaning as we'll see it was sort of unknown about
before, מושכב
כדרכו mushkav kedarko, *mushkav kedarko*, and it is buried and it's lying
down normally, like the normal way you would bury a body and
we'll see in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* what that's coming to exclude.
נוטלו ואת תפוסתו *notlo v'et tfusato*, then you remove it and you
take the תפוסה Tfusa *tfusa* like לתפוס *l'atpis* to grab onto, but
basically what it means is as we'll see in the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* some of the dirt underneath it where you're essentially afraid that
some of the bodily fluids have entered into. And you're going to
basically rebury it. And the reason you're going to be reburying it
is because this was presumably right in the middle of the road.
It was discovered and you don't want to make this impossible for
כהנים kohanim *kohanim* and נזירים *nezirim* to walk through and עושי פסח
*osei pesach* I guess. So anyway you want to relocate it to
a cemetery. Okay, so you're allowed to and you dig it up
and rebury it and you do it with some of the surrounding
dirt.
What you worry about is the dead bodies and that are exposed?
Yeah, you're buried bodily fluids and whatever. What? I mean, yeah, I
mean the reason for the dirt is less a concern about טומאה
tumah *tumah* and just I think a real concern about the קבורה
*kevura*, you know, you don't want to—you're right it could be if
it's—you gotta
bury it somewhere else in the ground maybe.
Right, but you don't want—yeah, it's true. It's a good question like
what's the big concern about the bodily fluids. I mean if these
will remain underground and I guess you want all the parts of
the מת meit *meis* buried together but it's a good point, like
if it's not—if it's just like fluids, then it wouldn't be causing
טומאה tumah. *tumah*.
Yeah, that's a good point I have to think about.
It's just that the body is now exposed, like the rain washed
the top soil away. Correct.
Right, I mean presumably if it's a coffin it all stayed in
the coffin, that's true. Yeah.
It's just that it had been buried and it's now exposed.
Something, yeah, exactly. You're doing some digging, exactly.
Exactly. Yeah, but it's a good question Michael's asking like why is
it important to dig up the fluids and rebury it, leave it
buried here. Presumably you want it all in the same place.
Do fluids from the body after the person has died not cause
טומאה tumah, *tumah*, correct?
Right. Well, no, they—I mean the problem is that they're just fluids,
meaning the things that cause טומאה tumah, *tumah* are flesh and blood
and bones and so on. Right. Okay, I mean there is this
thing—these things about נצל *neitzel* and whatever which might be a little
related. Anyway, שנים נוטלן ואת תפוסתן *shnayim notlan v'et tfusatan*. If there
are two bodies, you get to—you take them and the surrounding dirt
and you rebury them. מצא שלשה *matza shlosha*, however if there are
three bodies that you discovered, אם יש בין זה לזה ארבע אמות
ammot. עד שמונה *im yeish bein zeh l'zeh arba amot ad shmoneh*,
if there are between them, you know, between four to eight אמות
ammot, *amot*. Now what exactly that means is a long תוספות Tosafot
*Tosafos* tries to figure it out based on a גמרא Gemara. *Gemara*
in בבא בתרא *Bava Basra* about how they would bury the bodies
in these כוכין *kuchim*. What are they called?
Sarcophagi. Sarcophagi, I guess. Crypts. Right. So what exactly would be the—what
does it mean? All three within four אמות ammot *amot*? Are there
two within four אמות ammot *amot*? But anyway somehow they're within a
range between four to eight אמות amot? *amot* that that would be
a normal way in which you would expect bodies to be buried
if they were buried in this crypt or buried in a cemetery.
Because if they're too compressed or if they're too spread out, you
don't—that wouldn't happen in a cemetery. If they're too compressed could be,
you know, God forbid some tragedy they were all buried in this
like—you know, in the same place, you know, in a similar grave
or something like that. And spread out it's just individual graves. But
within this range of four to eight, that's the amount that you
find—What
did they bury
between four to eight אמות amos *amot*? Again that's not clear. תוספות
Tosafot *Tosafos* says that there are two bodies within four אמות amos
*amot*. He doesn't exactly explain the eight אמות *amot*. But somehow within
a range of four to eight, whether it means all three are
between—are between four to eight אמות *amot*. Could be, yeah.
There's a diagram here if you want—anybody.
Yeah so what does the diagram show?
The three, I think they're discussing are up on the top
of the crypt
and then the others are parallel below.
Right, that's what a crypt would look like. How does it describe
the four to eight אמות *amot*? Does it describe what's within the
four to eight אמות *amot*? תוספות Tosafot *Tosafos* has a couple of
possibilities that he's working through. Right, okay so anyway in that case,
so a type of a range that it's expected that that would
all be a normal—what you'd expect in a crypt or in a
graveyard. So הרי זה שכונת קברות Shchunat Kvarot, *harei zeh shechunat kvarot*,
that's therefore a literally a neighborhood of graves, meaning it's a graveyard.
And because you might have a graveyard here that nobody knew about,
what do you have to do? בודק ממנו ולהלן עשרים אמה bodek
mimenu u-le-hallan esrim ammah. *bodeik mehemenu u'lehalan esrim ama*. Now you have
to check from this 20 אמה ammah *ama*. Now the question is,
does it mean like a 20 אמה ammah *ama* radius or does
it mean you know 20 אמה ammah *ama* from the
feet toward, why— Or in all so there's some question not in
our גמרא Gemara actually but another גמרא Gemara that asks in which
directions are you checking the twenty אמות. But okay, the simple sense
is that it's a twenty אמה ammah radius. ומצא אחד בסוף עשרים
אמה. u-matza echad be-sof esrim ammah. Now if you find another grave
within twenty אמות, so בודק ממנו ולהלן עשרים אמה. ammah So then
you have to check from that one twenty אמות because now that
you know it's a graveyard you have to give yourself a bigger
radius and if you find any one, then it might be the
graveyard's continuing. רגליים לדבר. raglayim la-davar.
Now that's the reason this whole thing is here, not because it's
about dead bodies which a lot of נזיר deals with about dead
bodies and טומאת התהום, tumat ha-tehom, maybe that's also part of it,
it's a טומאת התהום, tumat ha-tehom, right? It was a buried טומאה
tumah that nobody knew about. But the תנאי t'nai seems to be,
and that's going to be in תנאי t'nai to another משנה, mishnah
רגליים לדבר. raglayim la-davar. You might remember in the previous one it
meant if the guy was already טמא tamei and then he became
טמא tamei again through טומאת התהום, tumat ha-tehom he's not saved from
it destroying his נזירות nezirot because טומאת התהום tumat ha-tehom. he's only
saved when it's a new טומאה. tumah If it's an extension of
an old טומאה, tumah then it does continue to undermine his נזירות.
nezirot. That was the previous משנה mishnah and it used the phrase
רגליים לדבר. raglayim la-davar. Now normally we take רגליים לדבר raglayim la-davar
to mean what this משנה mishnah, says it means, which means there's
good circumstantial evidence. It's actually a phrase we're gonna see a good
deal when we get to סוטה Sotah just in a few days,
right? But in the first משנה Mishnah it didn't mean circumstantial evidence,
it just sort of meant there's a pre-existing basis. It already started
off being טמא, tamei, so once it already had that base of
being טמא, tamei, he remains טמא tamei even based on טומאת התהום.
tum'at hatehom. Here presumably the reason it's being brought in again, maybe
they're dealing with buried dead bodies, that's one similarity, and the other
is this phrase רגליים לדבר. raglayim la-davar. But here רגליים לדבר raglayim
la-davar means what it normally means, that there's a good reason to
suspect that there is a cemetery here, so therefore you have to
be checking in the whole
environment. Okay. שאילו תחילה מצאו, she-ilu techillah matza'o, if you had just
found this stuff, this one, now here it means the one that
was twenty אמה ammah away, right? If you'd just found the one
that was twenty אמה Amma away, what would you have done? You
wouldn't say it's a graveyard, you would have twenty אמה away and
presumably there's nothing in its immediate vicinity even had you checked, so
you would have said okay it's a lone grave, נוטל את תפוסתו,
notel et tfusato, you would have just removed it with the dirt
with it. But now because you found it within twenty אמה of
this collection of graves, now we say it's part of the graveyard
and you have to go on checking. And by the way what's
not explicit in this משנה Mishnah but is pretty maybe implicit or
whatever spelled out in the גמרא Gemara is once it's a graveyard
you don't disinter the graves. You're only allowed to move the grave
to a place that's not so much in the public is because
it's not a graveyard and we assume that the body was buried
here because of the urgency of the exigencies of the moment.
Why would somebody bury a body in the middle of the road
and not go to a graveyard? So I don't know, somebody died
on the trip, imagine the ancient times, you die and somebody dies
on the trip, you gotta keep on moving, you don't want to
be out exposed in the middle of the night, what do you
do? You take the body with you and so they bury the
person there. Sort of like יעקב Yaakov and רחל, Rachel, ותיקבר שם
בדרך אפרת. va-tikaver sham be-derech Ephrat. So
she was buried right,
nice building with a dome and everything.
I think they came a little later.
Anyway, so therefore this is a body that really was not meant
to be here permanently, maybe they were planning on coming back and
removing it, maybe it didn't fully have rights to be here permanently,
you don't bury something in the public domain. So in those cases
it's just there by chance, you disinter it. But if it turns
out it's a graveyard, then it's the opposite. It's that somebody didn't
know and built a road over a graveyard, there was already a
graveyard here, so that belongs and there's a right to be there
and you're not allowed to disinter, and therefore you keep it there
and then you have to re-direct your road. So that's not spelled
out in the משנה, Mishnah but it's a little implicit. Like if
it was a lone grave you would have disinterred it. Now it's
a graveyard, you gotta know its parameters and you don't disinter. Yeah.
So I'm trying to understand what the last few words are adding,
שאילו תחילה מצאו נוטל את תפוסתו. she-ilu techillah matza'o notel et tfusato.
I'm not sure what that's saying that we didn't know already.
Yeah, it's trying to just explain to you
to appreciate how you're re-interpreting it based on context. If you'd just
dug one grave, found one grave, and then you even let's say
you were going to be proactive, nobody's requiring you to check the
environment with one grave by the radius, but you even went ahead
and you checked the radius and you checked ten feet around, you
would have found nothing. So even if you let's say you had
checked twenty feet around and you would have found another grave twenty
feet away, twenty feet not twenty אמות away, you still wouldn't have
said it was a graveyard, you wouldn't have had to do anything.
But now because you started with a collection of three graves and
now this is within that twenty אמה radius, you have a different
interpretation of what this means.
Right. In that first
case it was more the second case where you found two bodies,
that sort of by
happenstance you were digging around, it didn't have to be exactly exactly
exactly.
Yes. I mean you might be digging the foundation of a house,
right? I mean that happens in Israel all the time, every time
they do a new construction they have to call the antiquities, right,
whatever, yeah. Yeah. Building a road's a big deal. There's no
road here.
It didn't say it's a road, right. I mean, whatever it is,
but if it's like, yeah, it could be in your backyard, you
know, it could be your field, they're going to the field. It's
true, right, it could be, yeah, exactly, exactly. I was giving you,
right, I was even to say it was a road and you
had a very sort of like, you know, sort of an urgent
reason to, to want to move it. But you're really allowed to
disinter and move it even if it's like, was in your backyard,
you know, whatever sort of it might have been. Yes.
This body is not considered a מת meit מצוה.
No,
it's already been buried.
The משנה Mishnah. is should you decide that you want to move
it, proceed as the following way. You're not obliged to.
Right, exactly, exactly. Meaning you're allowed to, it's taking an assumption that
you would want to, I mean, you found a body buried here,
who wants to leave it, yeah, I want to get it away,
wherever the here is, want your bodies in the graveyard so the
rest, but yes, you're not obligated if you wanted to leave it
there and put up a, you know, yeah, you'd totally be allowed
to. Exactly. All right, so let's look at the
גמרא. Gemara אמר רב יהודה, Amar Rav Yehuda, says רב יהודה, Rav
Yehuda,
מצא פרט למצוי. matza prat le'matzuy. Now what they're doing is they're
interpreting every phrase in the משנה Mishnah means, which is fine, clearly
the משנה Mishnah indicates a list of criteria, so it's coming to
say to exclude other cases. But what's funny still is the language
used. This פרט לזה, prat lezeh, this פרט לזה, prat lezeh, which
is sort of like a דרשה derashah language, right, so they're almost
דרשנינג darshaning the משנה. Mishnah. But the reality is that the משנה
mishna. is giving a list of criteria, so it's coming to exclude
other things. So okay, you discovered it, as opposed to had it
been known. Right, if there was known to have been a grave
here, okay, then, then this has a right to be here and
you don't get a right to disinter it.
So, מת, meit if it was dead, פרט להרוג, prat le'harug, if
it had been murdered. Okay, now, why do you not get to
redisinter this in these cases? So the הרוג harug is going to
be based on a line the גמרא's Gemara about to say, which
is that if only if it's whole does this principle apply. Now
even so that sort of begs the question, you know, why? I
mean, it's just as likely that it's even more likely that this
thing was temporarily buried here and doesn't really belong here.
Well, no, if it's like a head here and a body there,
then you're just burying the body away from the head.
Oh, that's
interesting,
maybe, if it's dismembered or something.
Well, we're going to get to that. Okay, so but yes, this
does not sound like תוספות Tosafot explains it's because a part is
missing, but that's not explicit at all. And let's keep on reading
a little bit.
מושכב mushkav, כדרכו, kedarko, מושכב, lying down, פרט ליושב, prat leyoshev, if
it was in a sitting position, כדרכו, the normal way, פרט לראשו
מונח בין ירכותיו, prat leroshon munach bein yarchosav, as opposed to if
it was sort of like fetal? What? Fetal position. Fetal position, right,
that's what that's called. Okay.
תני עולא בר חנינא, Tani Ulla bar Chanina, מת שחסר אין לו
תפיסה, meit she'chasar ein lo tfisah, if it is a now now
let's see now this also explains what's the consequence if it doesn't
satisfy these criteria, so let's take a look. If it is missing
of some of, you know, it's not whole, so you don't take
the dirt around it, ולא שכונת קברות, velo shechunas kvaros, and if
you find three of them, you don't have to assume that the
whole area is a graveyard. וכל הני מאי טעמא לא אמרן, vechol
hanei mai ta'ama lo amran, so that's in terms of if it's
missing. But what about the other things that we're excluding? What's the
reason we exclude them? דלמא עובדי כוכבים הם, dilma ovdei kochavim hem,
because it's not the normal way for Jews to be buried, sitting
up or fetal position or whatever, so therefore we assume that it's
a non-Jew. And therefore what? So this is very, very confusing. Therefore
what? Therefore I guess we're not concerned with טומאה, tumah. so you
don't have to move it. I mean, what what is the consequence
if it doesn't satisfy these criteria and what's the logic behind it?
So let's first start with this idea that if it's missing, if
it's not whole, it doesn't have, you don't take the dirt around
it and it doesn't have the the idea of a graveyard. So
first of all, that does not sound like you don't you're not
allowed to disinter it. Actually you are allowed to disinter it, it's
actually more lenient. You can disinter but you don't have to worry
about the dirt around it and even if you find three, you
don't have to worry. Now
תוספות Tosafot asks what
the
logic is. מת שחסר אין לו שכונת קברות, meit she'chasar ein lo
shechunas kvaros, so now he deals with that. קשה להבין. kasheh lehavin.
למה? lamah? Why? Good question. ושמא הלכה
למשה
מסיני הוא, veshema halachah leMoshe miSinai hu,
which is now always like, okay, we can't explain it so הלכה
למשה מסיני, halachah leMoshe miSinai, which normally would be a really like,
you know, cheap answer, but we've been saying הלכה למשה מסיני halachah
leMoshe miSinai left and right in this מסכת, masechet, so it's not
at least it's a anyway, possible. But the question is, what are
the other things in exception of in the cases where it might
be a non-Jew? So is it because is it because it's a
non-Jew, you're still, no, is it, it might be you're still entitled
to disinter it? Why should you not be entitled to disinter it?
Okay, but maybe again for some reason you don't have to be
as strict and take the dirt around it or does it mean
that it doesn't have a שכונת קברות, Shchunat Kvarot that if it's
three of them, you don't have to worry again? Maybe it's just
an issue, we're not as strict, you don't have to be חושש
לחשש, Choshesh Lechashash, you don't have to take the dirt around it,
but presumably you would be allowed to disinter it. The only one
that presumably is saying that you're not allowed to disinter is the
first case, פרט למצוי, Prat L'matzuy, that you knew it was there.
Somebody says, 'How could you? What, you didn't know? Of course, we
always knew there was a grave there.' In that case, there's a
sense of you knew it was there, belonged there, and therefore had
a right to be there and you're not allowed to disinter. Yes.
No, he's saying the Bronze Age probably have the same problem as
we have in terms of every time you have a,
you want to build a house, you have to go and check,
right? So these could be Bronze Age burials and they could be
all over the place. Right, especially if they're in the fetal and
sitting position. Right. And so they just they have to have some...
Right, that's the way it was, Bronze Age burials were in the
sitting position? Oh, I didn't know that. So I grew, okay, interesting.
Aha.
So most of them are sitting.
I see. So basically, right.
So that means it would make sense that they would have to
have some kind of leniency to deal with the because they probably
have a lot of them.
Right, right, that's a good point. Now the point also is that
if it's if we really do assume it's non-Jews, maybe it means
you don't have to disinter, you can leave it there and you
don't even have to and you can ignore it, because if it's
a non-Jew then it's not מטמא באוהל, Metamei B'ohel, assuming that we're
פוסק Paskening that way. Right, so then you don't so that's another
possibility here, that if it's non-Jews, it doesn't mean it doesn't just
mean you can disinter with more leniencies, maybe it just means that
you can
completely like move on, right? Because it's not, you can assume it's
not מטמא באוהל. Metamei B'ohel. Yes.
Shouldn't the, you know, laws of the of ספקות, Sfekot, yeah, shouldn't
it be that if you find a body, majority of the corpses
are
non-Jews?
Oh, in any place? Well, I guess the question is if it's
in Israel, I mean I guess the question is how deep are
you digging and like what degree?
I'm serious. Yeah. What?
גדודא? Gduda? No, but the משנה mishna. is the even though the
גמרא Gemara is בבל, Bavel, it's explaining the משנה. Mishnah The משנה'ס
Mishnah's point of reference is Israel.
It would depend where. קיסריא Keisarya was mostly non...
Right, right. Yeah. So I don't know, it's not taking those into
account. Okay, so let's now as the גמרא Gemara continues. מצא שנים,
ראשו של זה בצד מרגלותיו של זה, וראשו של זה בצד מרגלותיו
של זה. Matza Shnayim, rosho shel zeh b'tzad marglotav shel zeh, v'rosho
shel zeh b'tzad marglotav shel zeh. There were two buried like parallel,
head to foot and head to foot. אין להם תפוסה ולא שכונת
קברות. Ein lahem tfusa v'lo shchunat kvarot. So there again you see
the exception is not that you have to leave them there, the
exception is you get to disinter them without the stringencies. You don't
have to take the dirt around it and you don't have to
worry if there are three of them. Again, somehow this is not
a normal type of a burial.
So I guess you could imagine that that you don't have to
worry about שכונת קברות Shchunat Kvarot. because it would not be the
normal way if it was a normal graveyard. You know, again, there's
some weird thing going on here. But again, maybe also it means
non-Jews. Jews don't bury this way. Maybe it means non-Jews, and again
maybe just have to be less concerned either to disinter them altogether
or to have these stringencies. מצא שלושה, אחד ידוע ושנים תחילה. Matza
shlosha, echad yadua u'shnayim techila. Now let's say you found three.
One was always known about, two that you just recently discovered. או
שנים תחילה ושנים ידועים, O shnayim techila u'shnayim yeduyim, or even two
were always known about and two are recently discovered. You found four?
Right.
So somehow switched gears there to אחד תחילה ושנים ידועים. Echad techila
u'shnayim yeduyim. Okay, to make it still three, if you look at
the right hand margin. אין להם תפוסה ואין להם שכונת קברות. Ein
lahem tfusa v'ein lahem shchunat kvarot. They don't have תפוסה Tfusa, or
שכונת קברות. Shchunat Kvarot Why not? That's a little bit bizarre, right?
I mean, so why's that different? So what? הלכה למשה מסיני. Halacha
LeMoshe MiSinai. הלכה למשה מסיני. Halacha LeMoshe MiSinai. So תוספות Tosafot says
that the the real חידוש, Chidush, again, I don't know what to
say about the תפוסה, but the real חידוש Chidush about שכונת קברות
Shchunat Kvarot, makes a certain amount of sense. You could say look,
if I didn't know about any three of them and I found
them, I could say that it was a forgotten graveyard. If I
knew about all three of them, it was a graveyard that was
known about. But if I knew about one and found two, or
knew about two and found one, then it's sort of like it
doesn't fall into either category, right? What I knew that there were
two graves here. If it was a graveyard, I would have known
it was a graveyard. But I didn't. All I knew was that
there were two graves. And if it was a forgotten graveyard, I
would have found three. So somehow it's like it doesn't fit either
so you don't have to assume it's a graveyard. You can assume
it's by chance. There were one or two that were known, there
was another by chance. You don't have to combine them and assume
it was a graveyard. So that at least explains the שכונת קברות,
shechunat kvarot? it doesn't explain the אין להם תפוסה. Ein lahem tfusa.
What?
The second תוספות Tosafot says on the first one, in the name
of the רשב"ם, Rashbam,
הלכה למשה מסיני, Halacha LeMoshe MiSinai, right, exactly. So whoever said that
was correct. All right, so then the גמרא Gemara, says like this.
מעשה ברבי ישבב שבדק ומצא שנים ידועים ואחד תחילה. Maaseh b'Rabbi Yeshevav
she'badak u'matza shnayim yeduyim v'echad techila. He found two that apparently were
known
about now and one he was a newly discovered. וביקש לעשותן שכונת
קברות. U'vikesh la'asotan shchunat kvarot. And he wanted to declare that this
was a graveyard and sort of check 20 אמה around and cordon
off the area. אמר לו רבי עקיבא. Amar lo Rabbi Akiva. Akiva
said to him כל שיגעת לריק יגעת Kol she'yagata l'rik yagata
all that effort is for nothing לא אמרו שכונת קברות אלא לג'
ידועים או לשלשה תחילה lo amru sh'chunat kvarot ela l'gimel yedua'im o
l'shlosha techila
only if all three were known initially or three brand new so
don't
go to לריק יגעת l'rik yagata and then leave for בהלה.
behala. Yeah it's right it's a very dramatic phrase also thinking about
these dead bodies I don't know to me it evokes קהלת Kohelet
all of our efforts are for naught right it's all הבל hevel
anyway very very morbid but but the point seems to be also
trying to protect and we're going to see this when we turn
the
page people from becoming טמא tamei declaring major areas of that were
public land or whatever you know off-limits right and so exactly. Okay
so נוטלן ואת תבוסתן notlan v'et t'vusatan you take them and the
dirt with them היכי דמי תבוסה heichi dami t'vusa what is this
thing that they grab onto the dirt with them אמר רב יהודה
אמר קרא amar Rav Yehuda amar kra or
sort of like where do we know this from אמיתתני ממצרים amitatni
mi'Mitzrayim take
me ממצרים mi'Mitzrayim
somehow that's with I don't know some of Egypt with me okay
you don't see that in the פסוק pasuk what can I do
Michael it's only smart people who can see that. Okay so טול
עמי tul imi take take some of מצרים Mitzrayim with me okay
and he
says like the whole point you know according to רש"י Rashi he
didn't want to be because אדמה טמאה adama t'meiah
I understand I
understand וכמה היא תבוסה v'kama hi t'vusa how much is it פירש
רבי אלעזר ברבי צדוק peirash Rabi Elazar b'Rabi Tzadok or just רבי
אלעזר Rabi Elazar נוטל עפר תיחוח notel afar tichuach
you take the dug dirt okay וחופר בבתולה v'chofir b'vetula and you
dig into even the virgin dirt that's underneath the מת meit ג'
אצבעות gimel etzbaot three fingers width because you assume it
soaked into the ground
right יעקב Ya'akov
was in the
I don't know I don't know what to tell you that's a
good point anyway because you assume that somehow the fluids will enter
in even into the
virgin dirt מיתיבי meitivei on this we have a ברייתא braita that
says
וכמה היא תבוסה v'kama hi t'vusa how much is it פירש רבי
אלעזר ברבי צדוק peirash Rabi Elazar b'Rabi Tzadok נוטל את הקיסמין ואת
הצרורות notel et hakismin v'et hatzrorot so here actually we're talking about
the what do you call it apparently we are talking about a
coffin because it says קיסמין kismin which are like the little
slivers splinters right so though interestingly תוספות Tosafot says that maybe it's
some of the stuff that's rubbed off of a marble coffin we'll
see why he's assuming marble in a minute but you take some
of the splinters and צרורות tzrorot תוספות Tosafot says are like the
like pottery shards okay which now exactly what those have to do
with anything he says צרורות אדמה tzrorot adama I'm trying to remember
why תוספות Tosafot says the צרורות tzrorot oh then he has another
explanation that יין yayin somehow some type of יין כוסס yayin koses
which is I don't know but רש"י Rashi says something yeah what
does רש"י Rashi say צרורות אדמה שנתהוו
מן הדם ומן המוח
tzrorot adama
shenit'havu min
hadam u'min hamuach
oh that they that they
somehow have absorbed some of it yeah so maybe they would have
some pottery shards there that would assume to have absorbed some of
the fluids okay so you take some of the splinters and the
pottery shards וזורק את הוודאין v'zorek et havada'in but here's the key
that's different you throw away the stuff that definitely has no part
of the מת meit there ומניח את הספקות u'maniach et hasfeikot and
you put aside the stuff that might have some of pieces of
the מת met or some of the fluids of the מת met
והשאר מצטרף v'hashar mitztaref and everything else presumably means everything that you
sort of know has the מת in it combines לרוב בנינו של
מת ולרוב מנינו ולמלא תרווד רקב l'rov binyano shel meit u'l'rov minyano
u'l'mlo tirvad rekav to count towards the amount of you know bones
and the amount of sort of stuff that's the you remember this
רקב rekav which is some of the what is it what I'm
sorry rot yeah that's a good translation the rot of the dead
body that a certain amount of it causes טומאה tuma so what's
different about this is it doesn't just say you don't just take
the entire soil you know the entire dirt you try to sift
it out and identify which parts really might have some of the
dead body there what's also significant and it gets back to Michael's
question about why you're removing it is that it seems to be
that you're removing the stuff that might actually cause טומאה tum'ah. not
just any fluids but the stuff that might actually cause טומאה how
you know so much that it like can add to like even
if you're taking stuff that you know has blood in it how
do you add that to this quantity of רוב בנינו rov binyano
and רוב מנינו rov minyano still like you're not presumably there's a
lot of dirt around you know you're not clearly just selecting out
little bits of bone you're taking the dirt that you think has
the bone in it but anyway exactly what that means that it's
מצטרף mitztaref to the שיעור shiur is a little bit unclear but
nevertheless it doesn't you don't just take the entire thing and you
don't take the virgin earth you only take the stuff that you
really you sift it out and you take the stuff that really
has some of the מת in it so yes
it adds to become a שיעור shiur
yeah that's what it sounds like but what does that mean it
comes to the שיעור shiur if you have dirt you know there's
little bits of bone in this dirt you're not going to add
the whole dirt to the שיעור shiur you'll only presumably add the
bone in the dirt but how exactly you measure that I mean
and it has to be pure
oh so that's what תוספות Tosafot says very good so that's why
תוספות Tosfos wanted to say that we were talking about a marble
coffin because this תרווד רקב tirvad rekav has to be pure when
it's to the dye but תוספות Tosfos it's really very hard to
explain if you take a look we'll read תוספות Tosfos in a
minute but let's first finish the
גמרא Gemara it says ולמלא תרווד רקב u'l'mlo tirvad rekav so alright
so you see it's not just this entire dirt and you have
to sort of sift it out הוא דאמר כי האי תנא hu
d'amar ki hai tanna no he says like the other תנא tanna
דתניא d'tanya How much is it? How much is it? אמר רבי
יוחנן משום בן עזאי. amar Rebbi Yochanan mishum Ben Azzai. So the
question is which רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan is this because סתם רבי
יוחנן stam Rebbi Yochanan is an אמורא. Amora. Anyway, נוטל עפר תיחוח
וחופר בשלושה אצבעות, notel afar tichuach vechofer bishlosha etzba'ot, exactly what was
said. No, it's just the entire layer of dirt, you don't try
to sift it out. Now if you take a look at this
question, right, what is this מלא תרווד רקב? mali tavard rekev? So,
let's, I mean actually let's just read תוספות מיתיבי, Tosfos Meisve, it'll
actually help clarify what this is.
וזורק את הודאיים. Vezorech et havadai'in. Alright, I'm going in תוספות Tosfos
four lines down where it says פירוש, peirush, beginning of a line.
מה שודאי לנו שאינו מן המת, Ma shevaday lanu she'eino min hamet,
you throw that away. ומניח את הספקות, Umeniach et hasveikot, מה שהוא
מסופק אם היה מן המת אם לאו, ma shehu mesupak im haya
min hamet im lav, מניח במקום המוצנע, meniach bimkom hamutznah, you put
it in a secluded place, שלא יטמאו אותו עושי טהרות, shelo yitme'u
oso osei taharot, that people shouldn't come in contact with it. So
here very much it's a concern about טומאה. והשאר שברור לו שמן
המת, Vehasar shebarur lo shemin hamet, stuff that you're clear, I presume
I guess the point means it's not just that it's mixed that
has pieces of the מת there, but it's something that you know
is actually a part of the מת itself, like separate from the
dirt. Okay, ברור לו שמן המת, barur lo shemin hamet, מצטרפין לרוב
בניינו או לרוב מניינו ולרובע
רובע הקב, mitztarfin lerov binyano o lerov minyano ulerov rov hakav, ולטמא
באוהל, Uletamei beohel, ולמלא תרווד רקב. ulemali tavard rekev. Okay, and then
he speaks about what כוסס koses means, he has another explanation. Okay,
so oh no, ויש אומרים כי כוסס כמין יין כוסס, veyesh omrim
ki koses k'min yayin koses, מיני
קיוהי ובשמים שמשימין בארון, minei ki'ui ubesamim shemasimin ba'aron, that maybe these
are like types of fragrances that they put in the ארון aron
so it wouldn't smell so much. קשיא, Kasha, and the, yeah, and
then you assume that maybe it absorbed some of the dead body.
Then he says וקשיא דאם כן אין לו רקב דנעשה גלגלין, vekasha,
de'im kein ein lo rekev, de'na'aseh gilgalin, then it wouldn't have the
law of רקב rekev because then it becomes a contaminant. מדי דהוי
נקבר בארון עץ, Midai d'havai nikbar be'aron etz, דאף שערו עמדו לגזוזה,
de'af sa'aro amlei ligzozeh, even hair that was ready to be cut,
איבעי ליה למיפרע הון ידלן ליעשה גלגלין. yiba'e lemiphra' hon yadlan lina'aseh
gilgalin. Okay, so basically, so he raises that question.
So to support the whole
idea of the רקב, rekev, you'd have to assume that there were
no foreign, all of these, you know, maybe some of it seeped
into the dirt afterwards, but it was not buried with any foreign
matter in it.
It seems to be the assumption in the way we're reading both
the תנא Tanna דאקסורציה? d'exorschia? Yeah, יוסף בן אלעזר? Yosef ben Elazar?
Yeah, and the תוספות Tosafos is that they, there was a practice
of burying them in wooden coffins.
Well תוספות Tosafos wants, well we, we said that well, oh I
see, well תוספות Tosafos actually said in order to deal with this
problem about, about contaminants that when it says ארון, aron, yeah, but
he says ארון של שיש, aron shel shayish, right?
Where is רש"י? Rashi? תוספות מיתיבי, Tosfos Meisve, the beginning מיתיבי. Meisve.
נוטל הקיסמין פירוש מן הארון של שיש שנכתת. Notel hakesamin, peirush min
ha'aron shel shayish shenichtat. That somehow the marble or whatever has been
ground because he didn't want it to be wood because that would
have been,
then you wouldn't have the רקב, rekev, you know.
No, but then also why would you have like, you know, fluids
seep out of the ארון aron and you know to the side?
Yeah, I don't know if it's marble how those fluids got so
far out. Anyway, alright, בודק הימנו, bodek himenu, let's keep on going.
אמר רבא, Amar Rava, בדק ופינה בדק ופינה בדק ואשכח
מהו. badak ufina, badak ufina, badak ve'ashkach, mahu.
So let's say basically what you did is you checked and you
found, you checked and you found, and then the third one you
found, okay, לא האי
מפני ליה לגבי הנך תרי ולא הני תרי לגבי האי חד. lo
hai mafni leh legabi hanach terei velo hani terei legabi hai chad.
So basically here's the question: let's say you had already disinterred the
two before you found the third. If you found all three, you
say uh-oh, I got a graveyard here, I got to leave them,
right? But let's say you had disinterred the two and then you
found the third. So what do you do now? Do you have
to, can you take the third one and move it as well
because you know you don't have a whole grave—you don't have three
here? Or do you have to bring those two back because now
they have a graveyard and they should remain where they were? So
רבא Rava says basically you keep things the way they were. לא
האי מפני ליה לגבי הנך תרי, lo hai mafni leh legabi hanach
terei, you don't—you're not entitled to remove the third one to the
other two because now you know it was part of a graveyard.
ולא הני תרי לגבי האי חד, velo hani terei legabi hai chad,
but you don't have to reinter those two to this one. Okay,
now, do you have to still check twenty אמות? You know that
he doesn't say, presumably because you know there was a graveyard here.
Okay, איכא דאמרי, ikka d'amri, but at least you don't have to
reinter those that you disinterred. איכא דאמרי, ikka d'amri, some say, אמר
רבא, amar Rava, כיון שניתנה רשות לפנות מפנה להון. keivan she'nasna reshut
lefanot, mefaneh lehawn. Okay, now once you've started disinterring, you can disinter
the third one as well, even though you know it's a graveyard,
but you know you've already started—started reburying it and let's face it,
there's a good reason why you want—ideally you don't want the bodies
here, they didn't belong here, I mean—Well
that'd be forced into six?
Well that's another question, do you have to keep on checking and
if you keep on checking are you allowed to continue
disinterring? Okay, but at least this third one you're allowed to disinter
since you already interred two. Okay, so גמרא Gemara says why is
this? ולישווינהו שכונת קברות? Velishavinhu shechunat kvarot? So why not make it
a שכונת קברות? shchunas kvaros. Meaning that's what it is! Why don't
you have to leave it where it is? So אמר ריש לקיש,
Amar Reish Lakish, אילו מצאו וטיהרו ארץ ישראל, ilu matzu v'tiharu Eretz
Yisrael, they found an excuse and they purified ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael.
Meaning, we would like to get— get everything, you know, all the
bodies in the graveyards and not have it scattered around. So once
we started disinterring, right, we allow ourselves to continue the process and
it gives us the opportunity. Search around now? What?
Search down three, but then the prescribed distance.
I know, but it's better if we take
those—if these that are in my backyard or in a field or
in a road or in a place where we're building a house,
it would be much better if we had a right to disinter
them and move them to a בית קברות. beis kvaros. That's right.
That's a good question. That's not clear. It sounds like maybe not.
It sounds like if we're אילו מצאו, ilu matzu, we're finding an
excuse, we get to say that it's not a שכונת קברות.
shchunas kvaros, So everyone should just bury, you know,
as you find them, rebury them before you go looking for more,
right? Could be, but it's very interesting, right, that you know, they're
on the one hand there's sort of a right of the body
to remain buried where it is and on the other hand there
is like, you know, communal societal needs, so where sort of, you
know, and you know, for כהנים kohanim and for other people, so
if we already started reinterring them, we're allowed—we allow ourselves to treat
it halachically differently. That's a good point. Yeah.
What? You know there's a graveyard there.
Well, you don't know for sure, maybe they're just three graves. Anyway,
I don't know. It's not clear whether you have to keep on
checking. It sounds like you don't, it sounds like you're done, right?
But you're right. I mean that's the עילא, eila, an excuse, like
willful ignorance. It's sort of maybe like תחום שבת techum Shabbos from
before, you know. You know, I understand. It is funny, you know.
The ראש Rosh says—what, the ראש Rosh has some line here, one
minute, he says like this, he
says—let me see the ראש, Rosh, he says like
this—yeah, if you look four, three lines down in the פירוש הרא"ש
perush haRosh in the wide lines, he says like this, אמר ריש
לקיש אילו מצאו ארץ ישראל בעלילה מועטת Amar Reish Lakish Ilu matzu
Eretz Yisrael ba'alila muetes with a with a small excuse ובסברא קטנה
uvisvara katana just a little bit of an argument טיהרו ארץ ישראל
משום כהנים ועושי טהרות. tiharu Eretz Yisrael mishum kohanim v'osei taharos.
So he makes it sound like not just in this case. Like
he makes it sound like in general, right, how can כהנים walk
around? Like how do we know which places are טהור tahor or
not? So we in general make it—we give a very low standard,
make it very—you know, use any excuse to try to explain that
there aren't problems in a particular place because you have to live
here. והכא נמי כיון שברשות פינום הדין התירו לפנות גם את הג'
Vehacha nami keivan shebirshus pinum hadin hatiru lifanos gam es ha'gimmel ולא
דמי לקבר ידוע דאסור לפנות דאין כאן ידיעה ודאית. v'lo dami l'kever
yadua d'asur lifnos d'ein kan yedia vada'is. We don't know for sure.
So yes, we sort of do know, but because when we found
the third it wasn't the other ones around. But again, it's quite
funny because if you think about it, right, the basic הלכה halacha
is that ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael is טהור tahor and there's the
טומאה of ארץ העמים, Eretz Ha'amim, right, of course the likelihood is
that outside of Israel there's a lot less fewer Jewish graves than
in Israel. So in Israel, so ארץ העמים Eretz Ha'amim is טמא,
tamei, ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael is טהור, tahor, but really we're now
finding out that they really just, you know, used any excuse to
say that a place was טהור tahor to make it more work
it out, you know, better. So that's what we're doing, okay? But
what's interesting about the ראש Rosh is he makes it sound like
it wasn't just in this one case, that there was like a
general—as a general, you know, a general operating principle we're finding ways
to claim that areas are טהור tahor even if a little investigation
we might discover more, you know. All right. What?
It's limited to ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, not necessarily for outside of
Israel. Right. I wonder if there's certain, you know, whatever, חוץ לארץ.
Chutz La'aretz.
Yeah, well it doesn't. Outside the opposite, we're using any excuse to
define it as טמא, tamei, right? ארץ העמים Eretz Ha'amim is טמא,
tamei, right? All right. So בדק כ' אמה ולא מצא מהו? Badak
kaf ama v'lo matza mahu?
You estimated this was outside of חוץ לארץ, Chutz La'aretz,
I mean I'm sorry outside of ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, this actually
was
in חוץ לארץ Chutz La'aretz
then you would...
I don't know, because on the other hand it's already ארץ העמים
Eretz Ha'amim is already טמא tamei and maybe it's non-Jewish graves, so
I don't know. It's a good question. בדק כ' אמה ולא מצא
מהו? Badak kaf ama v'lo matza mahu? Now you checked twenty אמות
and you didn't find, what's the story?
So you think you're done. So אמר רב נחמן בר ירמיה אמר
רב שכונת קברות. Amar Rav Nachman bar Yirmya amar Rav Shchunas Kvaros.
So oh, wait, let me understand. Wait, wait, let
me—one minute.
Oh, right, right. So the point is the way תוספות Tosfos explains
the question, you check twenty אמות in one direction, do you have
to check in the other directions as well? But תוספות doesn't really
understand that question because why would one direction, just because you didn't
find in one direction, but you know, doesn't mean... so the graveyard
might be going in the other direction. Who knows which end you
are. So anyway, but that's the way he understands the question, though
he points out the problems with it.
And then says—no and then the answer שכונת קברות, shchunas kvaros normally
שכונת קברות shchunas kvaros is a חומרא, chumra, here he understands it
as a
קולא. kula. No, you can assume what you found is the end
of the שכונת קברות and you don't have to keep on checking.
So it doesn't really fit the words and doesn't make so much
sense, but that's the way תוספות reads it. מאי טעמא אמר ריש
לקיש אילו מצאו טיהרו את ארץ ישראל. Mai ta'ama amar Reish Lakish
Ilu matzu tiharu es Eretz Yisrael. So that's the same answer. Now
the ראש Rosh has a different read about this. The ראש Rosh
doesn't like any of those reads and the ראש's Rosh explanation is
the following.
Let me find it. He goes through all the other reads and...
He goes through all the other possible reasons as they don't make
any sense. And then he says hold on ונראה לי לפרש. v'nireh
li l'fareish.
Okay, it's two lines from the bottom in the
Rosh. בדק ולא מצא מאי? badak v'lo matza mai? ומיבעיא ליה אם
מותר לפנות ג' מכאן u'mibaya lei im mutar l'fnot gimmel mikan דקודם
בדיקה חיישינן שמא מערות היו כאן מתוקנים וקבורים, d'kodem bdika chaishinan shema
me'arot hayu kan metukanim v'kvurim, that you start three, so you say
that it's a שכונת קברים shchunat kvarim and that's forced you to
check. Okay, so you're going to assume if it is a שכונת
קברים shchunat kvarim you're going to find more. What did you do
though? You started the three, you checked all around 20 ammas in
all directions and you found nothing. So at the end of the
day, there's only three in a 20 amma radius. Maybe it's not
a שכונת קברים, shchunat kvarim, right? You understand? Now maybe I can
actually disinter the three. Okay, וכיון דבדק ולא מצא הוי דבר שאין
כאן שכונת קברים אין דרך לקבור מתים אלא במקום המיוחד לקבורים
הרבה. v'keivan d'badak v'lo matza havei davar she'ein kan shchunat kvarim ein
derech likvor meitim ela b'makom hamyuchad l'kvurim harbeh. So three made me
think it's a שכונת קברים shchunat kvarim but now I checked a
20 amma radius and there was nothing else. So now maybe I
actually can disinter it. So then the answer is no, you can't
disinter it. הרי זה שכונת קברים harei zeh shchunat kvarim ופשיטא ליה
כיון דג' הם מוחזק ליה שכונת קברים אף על פי שלא מצא.
u'pshita lei keivan d'gimmel hem muchzak lei shchunat kvarim af al pi
shelo matza. That
even three is enough to assume that they were intentionally buried here,
it even was maybe it was a small graveyard, but you cannot
move even if you check and all you have is those three.
So then the
answer, ולא גרסינן הכא מאי טעמא אמר ריש לקיש אילו מצאו. v'lo
garsinan hacha mai ta'ama amar Reish Lakish ilu matzu. That was miscopied
from above, says the Rosh. So it sounds like it's a חומרא
chumra but then you don't understand the אילו מצאו. ilu matzu. So
the Rosh does away with that line. Or you try to read
it as a קולא, kula, okay, which is how תוספות reads it
but then it doesn't fit the words so well. All right, so
that, yeah?
Does that mean the Rosh had a manuscript in which... No, I
don't...
no. He's speculating, yeah, which happens all the time, yeah.
In terms of contemporary הלכה, halacha, I guess the sense that אילו
מצאו ilu matzu was kind of the the technique, the operating principle,
right? I mean there's all kinds of situations where...
In this case, you mean?
No, in general. I mean, general situations come up where for various
reasons you want or need to disinter a body and...
Right, right, right, right.
I can't tell you about how this gets applied in contemporary הלכה,
halacha, but yeah, I mean I assume, you know, look, that happens
all the time. I mean I bet that the people that are
digging in Israel and have to go ahead and call the antiquities
department would love to be able to say אילו מצאו, ilu matzu,
right? Every place you dig, you gotta stop, you can't whatever, right?
Let's find an excuse that we can disinter this and move it
and get on with what we're doing, you know. So yeah.
I actually find she has two תשובות teshuvot on this with a
graveyard in Russia. Oh yeah? Moving them in Russia. And I can
check and see but I believe...
He finds a good אילו ilu to do it. Could
be, right.
I happened to see on TV last week, there's an old movie
Deliverance. Yeah, in the backwoods of Georgia.
I don't remember, yeah.
And they're taking this trip through this area that's gonna be flooded
a huge, you know, area.
Right. And one of the last scenes is they're digging up, moving
graves, moving an entire graveyard. Wow, wow, yeah.
Deliverance? Deliverance.
Okay.
All right. Let's take... All right. Next משנה. Mishnah כל ספק נגעים
בתחלתה טהור. kol safek negaim bit'chilatah tahor. So this also this says
nothing really to do except what you'll see certain the some parallels
just in the in the structure. כל ספק נגעים בתחלתה טהור. kol
safek negaim bit'chilatah tahor.
All doubts of of נגע, nega, נגע צרעת, nega tzara'at, if it's
a doubt initially it's טהור tahor עד שלא נזקק לטומאה. ad shelo
nizkak l'tumah. Before the while, you know, so if the person is
not yet טמא tamei and you don't know if this נגע nega
makes them טמא, tamei, so you're lenient and you basically rule he's
טהור tahor before while since that his that's his current status quo.
לטומאה, l'tumah, עד שלא נזקק לטומאה. ad shelo nizkak l'tumah. משנזקק לטומאה,
mishenizkak l'tumah, once a person is טמא tamei and you wanted to
know has the נגע nega gone away, is the person טהור, tahor,
and you have a doubt, then you say ספיקו טמא, sfeko tamei,
then you say they're טמא. tamei. So that functions on, remember that
principle about טומאת התהום. tum'at hatehom, If you were already טמא tamei
and there's a question of טומאת התהום, it extends your טומאה. Right?
That's רגליים לדבר raglayim l'davar מפני שחזקתן טמא, mipnei she'chezkatam tamei, right?
So before we used the phrase רגליים לדבר raglayim l'davar talking about
the graveyard, here we're using the concept of status quo. If the
status quo was you were טהור tahor and we have a doubt
if this is a נגע צרעת, nega tzara'at, we'll declare you to
be טהור, tahor, we'll assume the status quo continues. If you were
טמא tamei and we have a doubt if this cleared up, we'll
declare you to still be טמא, tamei, right? So it's the continuation
of the status quo. That's the way it's that's why we're having
this משנה. Mishnah The Rosh gives the following example. Like normally if
you hear ספק, safek, you know, question is, well, is this the
right color, is this the right size, is this the right whatever?
But you know, but those kinds of questions like shouldn't you be
able to know that if you just are, you know, if you,
you know, know the criteria? So the Rosh gives the follow... he
quotes from משניות in נגעים Negaim and he gives the following criteria,
okay. Two people come to me, I'm the כהן, Kohen, and one
of them has a little spot and the other has a spot
the size of a גריס. gris. Okay, and by the way, the
only it has to be the size of a of a little
bit bigger than a גריס gris in order to be a proper
problem. So I lock them up and I tell them come back
next week. They come back next week, they're both the size of
a גריס. Gris. Now the point is, the one who was always
the size of a גריס Gris is טהור; Tahor; it didn't spread
and it was never the minimum size. The one who started smaller
and now is a גריס Gris is actually טמא Tamei because it
spread. But I somehow forgot who was who. And they also somehow
forgot who was who. Okay, so in that case, they're both טהור.
Tahor. Even though one of them objectively is טמא, Tamei, but since
I don't know which one that is, they're both טהור. Tahor.
So the one who had already the size of the גריס, Gris,
you didn't call him טמא Tamei to begin with why?
Because I wanted to see if it, no, no, it had to
be a גריס ועוד. Gris va'od. So I wanted to see if
it was going to spread. Okay, so one of them spread and
the other one didn't spread. Okay, so the reverse case is that
now these, is that two people come to me with a, one
guy, oh, let me see if I get this right. Hold on.
Not a גריס, Gris, I'm sorry, it was a סלע. Sela. סלע,
Sela, a coin. I'm sorry, I'm sorry, it was a סלע. Sela.
The גריס, Gris, I'm sorry, סלע ועוד. Sela va'od.
Is that bigger than a גריס?
Gris? Yes, סלע Sela is bigger than a גריס. Gris. Okay, I'm
sorry.
Okay, so someone came to you already the נגע nega was the
size of a סלע? Sela?
Two people came to me at the same time. I locked them
both up. They came back a week. One guy spread, the other
didn't. And I didn't know which was which.
They didn't have the סימנים simanim in נגעים. Negaim.
Correct. Well, no, no, hold on, wait a minute.
Because of white hairs or whatever it is.
Yeah, yeah, okay, wait a minute, we'll get to that anyway. Hold
on, let me just do the other one. Okay, now the other
case is like this.
Ah, okay. So here, ah, here the case was like this. So
now two people came to me, same story. One was a גריס
Gris and one was a סלע. Sela. I locked them both up.
They came back a week later. Now they were both a סלע
ועוד. Sela va'od. So they're both טמא. Tamei. They both spread for
both of them, they're both טמא. Tamei. Okay, lock them up again.
Then after a week, they both come back. Whatever, they're both טמא.
Tamei. I mean, whatever, they're now טמא Tamei until it clears up.
They come back and then now they both are back to a,
they now they both are back to a סלע. Sela. So the
one who started as a סלע, Sela, or they're both like under
a סלע. Sela. Whatever, how does it go? They're both, wait a
minute.
Right. So now, so now the point is like this. When will
they become טהור? Tahor? They'll become טהור Tahor when it gets back
to the, okay, it started off, one had a גריס Gris and
one had a סלע. Sela. I locked them up, they came back
a week with both סלע ועוד. Sela va'od. So they both had
spread, they're both טמא. Tamei. When are they going to be טהור?
Tahor? When it goes back to the size that it had initially,
okay, when the size that they had at the very beginning. So
for the one that it started off as a סלע, Sela, he'll
be טהור Tahor when it goes back to a סלע. Sela. For
the guy who started off as a גריס, Gris, he's not going
to be טהור Tahor when it goes back to a סלע. Sela.
He's only going to be טהור Tahor when it goes all the
way back to a גריס. Gris. Right? It has to go back
to the, so the guy who started smaller, it has to fully
reverse itself to the size it was initially. Wow, what, that's the
הלכה. halacha. So now they come back to me and now they're
both back down to a סלע. Sela. So one of them is
טהור, Tahor, the guy who started as a סלע Sela is טהור.
Tahor. And we don't know who is who. And the other one
is טמא. Tamei. And we don't know which is which. So in
that case, they both remain טמא. Tamei. Okay, so it's the same
type of an idea. I just get confused who is who. In
one case, so when they, when one of them, when they started
as טהור Tahor and I don't know which is טמא, Tamei, they're
both טהור. Tahor. When they started as טמא Tamei and I don't
know which one became טהור, Tahor, they're both טמא. Tamei. Okay, so
that's the principle. You retain the status quo. So let's see what
the גמרא Gemara says. מנא הני מילי, Mena hani milei, where's this
from? אמר רב יהודה אמר רב, Amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav, אמר
קרא, amar kra, the verse says לטהרו או לטמאו. letaharo o letame'o.
So it says this will be, this is the נגע צרעת nega
tzara'at to make it טהור Tahor or טמא. Tamei. הואיל ופתח בו
הכתוב בטהרה תחילה. ho'il ufataḥ bo hakatuv betahara techila.
Since it first says you're מטהר metaher it, we see that there's
an inclination to say you're טהור. Tahor. So therefore, if you start
טהור, Tahor, you stay טהור. Tahor. So אי הכי, ei hachi, says
the גמרא, אפילו משנזקק לטומאה נמי ספיקו טהור. afilu mishenizkak letuma nami
sefeko tahor.
But it doesn't say that that's only when you start טהור. Tahor.
If you want to say the פסוק pasuk starts by saying לטהרו,
letaharo, you should be inclined to say טהור, Tahor, then that should
be even if there's, if the guy started off as being טמא,
Tamei, if there's a doubt you should say טהור. Tahor. So that's
not telling you that principle. אלא כי איתמר דרב יהודה אמר רב
אהא איתמר. ela ki itmar deRav Yehuda amar Rav aha itmar. This
idea according to this פסוק pasuk was said for the following הלכה.
halacha. That the idea really that you keep the status quo is
not based on this פסוק. pasuk. You keep the status quo is
just based on a general principle that you assume a status quo,
you go by חזקה. Chazaka. Okay, so that's what it's based on.
So if they started טהור Tahor and there's a doubt and you
don't know which one became טמא, Tamei, you say they're both טהור.
Tahor. And if they started טמא Tamei and you don't know which
became טהור, Tahor, you say they're both טמא. Tamei. That's the principle
you go by חזקה. Chazaka. And this פסוק pasuk is telling you
a different הלכה. halacha. Okay, it's telling you the following. אלא כי
איתמר דרב יהודה אמר רב אהא איתמר. ela ki itmar deRav Yehuda
amar Rav aha itmar. אם בהרת קדמה לשיער לבן טמא, im beheret
kadma lese'ar lavan tamei, ואם שיער לבן קודם לבהרת טהור. ve'im se'ar
lavan kodem labeheret tahor. So basically the
So basically the פסוק pasuk says, right, והיא הפכה שיער לבן, Ve'hi
hafecha se'ar lavan,
that the בהרת baheret turns the hair white. So it means that
the hair had to first be a different color, you had the
בהרת, baheret, and then the בהרת baheret turned the hair in it
white. But if it started white, then the בהרת baheret didn't turn
it white. So basically, so if the בהרת baheret came first, then
it is טמא tamei and then it turned the hair white, or
the
hair became white after the בהרת, baheret, it's טמא. tamei. ואם שיער
לבן קודם לבהרת טהור, Ve'im se'ar lavan kodem le'baheret tahor, but if
it was always white, טהור, tahor, then it's טהור tahor because the
בהרת baheret did not turn the hair white. ספק, Safek, if you
don't know which came whether it was always white or it became
white after the בהרת, baheret, טמא, tamei, then it's טמא. tamei. So
that's actually interesting because that's a case you would say, you know,
why don't you just say the guy's טהור, tahor, you go by
his חזקה, hazakah, you don't know which is which, right, it's not
like the case of two guys, right? So but that's a case
that's come out a little different that you have both of the
סימנים, simanim, you just don't know which order they came in. רבי
יהושע אומר כהה. Rabbi Yehoshua omer kehe. Rabbi Yehoshua says it's כהה.
kehe. מאי כהה, Mai kehe, what does that mean? אמר רב יהודה
כהה וטהור. Amar Rav Yehuda kehe ve'tahor.
Okay, it means that he said it was טהור. tahor. And גמרא
כהה וטמא, kehe ve'tamei, maybe it means he said it was כהה
kehe and טמא, tamei, which is bizarre. כהה Kehe means כהה הנגע
keha hanega means that it lightened and that it's טהור. tahor. And
also then he'd be saying the same thing as the תנא קמא.
Tanna Kamma. So the ראש Rosh says it's just a way of
saying why does he say it's טהור? tahor? What is the reason
that he says it's טהור? tahor? So אמר רב יהודה אמר רב
אמר קרא לטהרו או לטמאו הואיל ופתח בו הכתוב בטהרה תחילה. Amar
Rav Yehuda amar Rav amar kra letaharo o letame'o ho'il ufatah bo
hakatuv betaharah techilah.
That since the פסוק pasuk started off with טהרה, taharah, therefore in
this case you don't know which came first, you say it's טהור.
tahor. I do have to tell you that I don't exactly understand
why this is why you need a special פסוק, pasuk, why this
isn't just the general rule that you go by the חזקה. hazakah.
But somehow if this is different than the doubt. The other case
was a doubt of which person is טמא, tamei, which person is
טהור. tahor. Here it's you don't know the order that it came,
and you basically presume טהרה. taharah. But the first principle is just
based on the principle of חזקה. hazakah. And my watch is a
little off. What time are we? 23. Okay, wow, so we have
six minutes.
Okay, and the משנה Mishnah itself says עד שלא
יוחזק בזיבה.
ad shelo
yuchzak bizivah. Yeah, so that's until you prove definitely
that he's a זב.
zav. Yeah, right, exactly. All right, so now penultimate משנה here, also
having nothing to do with נזירות, Nezirut, but just picking up on
the phrase of רגליים לדבר, raglayim ladavar, and the last משנה will
get us back to נזירות. Nezirut. So let's take a look. בשבעה
דרכים בודקים את הזב. Beshiv'ah derachim bodkim et hazav.
In seven ways you check the man with the—with the flow—he has
a penile emission, it's not semen, okay, it's something. By a woman
the difference between a נידה niddah and a זבה zavah is when
is she bleeding? During her menstrual period or not during her menstrual
period, but it's always about blood. By a man the difference between
בעל קרי, ba'al keri, a man with a seminal emission, and a
זב, zav, is what is—what is being emitted? Is it semen or
is it something else? So therefore what is this so you're it's
that's number one. And therefore when the there is this other fluid,
so A, there's a question about what the fluid looks like, and
that's another discussion, but there's also a point about making sure that
it did not come out as a reject as—as a result of
some type of a process that was like ejaculation of semen, some
type of a thing that would have been through sort of sexual
stimulation or something of that or it was through אונס, oness, through
some other type of a thing that was some other cause. It
cannot be through some other cause. Okay, so let's take a look.
So בשבעה דרכים בודקים את
הזב, beshiv'ah derachim bodkim et hazav, you check seven ways to make
sure there was not some other cause that led to this flow.
עד שלא נזקק לזיבה, ad shelo nizkak le'zivah, before he's declared a
זב. zav. Only when he has two of these emissions is he
declared a זב. zav. במאכל ובמשתה, Bemachal uv'mishteh,
maybe there was something he ate that caused it or drank, that's
two. במשא, Bemassa, maybe he carried something heavy, exertion caused it. ובקפיצה,
Uv'kfitzah, or he jumped and that somehow, you know, over also type
of exertion. ובחולי, Uv'choli, or he's sick.
All these are reasons to be lenient. If any of these are
factors, then we say it's a result of these and it's not
זיבה. zivah. Right, if he's not yet a זב, zav, meaning he
has not yet seen twice, which would make him a זב.
zav. Remember by a woman jumping, remember? Right.
So by a woman the הלכה halacha is that a woman becomes
a נידה niddah or זבה zavah even מחמת אונס, machmat oness, even
if it specifically mentions jumping or carrying things, it's whatever. The man
however the זיבה zivah is only when it's not due to these
external factors. Okay,
ובמראה ובהרהור, Uv'mareh uv'hirhur, מראה mareh something he looked at and presumably
that's connected to הרהור hirhur although they're counted as separate, which caused
some type of a sexual stimulation, okay, and therefore maybe that was
a factor.
Okay, you don't see זב zav as a type of.
Yes, so that's the funny thing, we you know we would normally
assume the whole point about it is that it's some type of
a חולי. choli. So the question is how much is the משנה
imagining or, you know, that it's something a little more, I don't
know, supernatural and not natural, not חולי, choli, exactly, because, you know,
normally I mean when people try to speculate what is the זיבה,
zivah, I think... I mean when people try to speculate what is
the זב, zav, I think they think it's some type of a
venereal disease that
causes these types of flows, which happens with some of them. But
yes, that is funny. Like, is it imagining this like a צרעת?
tzaraat? Like it has to be something that's not natural, right? I
don't know. Okay. משנזקק לזיבה, Mishenizkak leziva, once however the person is
declared a זב, zav, he flows twice, now if he—the relevance is
once he's already a זב zav and had two flows, if he
sees a third flow, he has to bring a קרבן. korban. It's
also relevant because he has to go seven days without a flow.
So let's say during those seven days, he has something, and it
was a flow, but maybe it's attributable to one of these other
causes. Does that mean he has to start his seven clean days
again? Okay, so once he's already a זב, zav, we discount, we
don't care about these causes. And we say if he flows, even
if these causes are present, it'll be a third flow to make
him a קרבן, korban, or if he's trying to get his seven
clean days and he has a flow, even if these other causes
are present, he has to start all over again.
Right, right, 100%. So either way, for the two orders of way
you need seven days, right? Only difference is the קרבן. korban.
קרבן, korban, right. Okay. אבל משנזקק לזיבה, Aval mishenizkak leziva, once he
became a זב, zav, and then he had these—another flow which could
be an issue to bring a קרבן korban or an issue to
start counting seven days again, אין בודקין אותו. ein bodkin oto. You
do not pay attention to these factors and it's—it's gonna be a
problem regardless. אונסו וספקו ושכבת זרעו טמאים. Onso vesfeko veshichvat zaro tme'im.
And in this case that he's already a זב, zav, things that
come as a result of אונס, ones, meaning some outside factor like
these things, or there's a doubt—we'll see what doubt means—or it's his
semen, and all these things we assume that they're טמאים. tme'im. Even
his semen we assume there's maybe it's really זיבה ziva that's in
his semen, we'll see about that. All these questions, once he was
a זב, zav, we just say that all of this is normal
זיבה ziva even when these other factors are present. Okay. Why? שרגלים
לדבר. Sheraglayim ladavar. Because that—once he's already a זב, zav, we assume
that everything else is a result of his condition and it's not
some other thing that's causing it. We know that he has this
condition, so everything is a result of this condition. Okay. המכה חברו,
Hamakeh chavero, last case of רגלים לדבר. raglayim ladavar. Somebody who smites
his friend, ועמדוהו למיתה, ve'amduhu lemitah, and they said—and it looked like
this guy was going to die and therefore they decided if the
guy would have died, this person would now be executed for having
committed murder. Okay. והקל ממה שהיה, Vehekel mimasheh haya, but then he
started getting better. All right, so the guy that was—that was killed,
it looked like he was—he was improving. And ולאחר מכאן הכביד ומת,
v'le'achar mikan hichbid umet, but then he had a—he had a relapse
and he died in the end. So do you say that the
death in the end was due to the first thing? Or was
that some—that was some you know, some new condition—I mean, it was
some complication that happened later, but we can't attribute it to the
act—to the original act. So in that case, חייב. chayav. We—the first
position is he is חייב, chayav, yes, in the end, the effect
that he got better doesn't counteract that it fits in the end
what we had predicted that he was going to die as a
result of the wound. רבי נחמיה אומר פטור. Rebbi Nechemiah omer patur.
No, רבי נחמיה Rebbi Nechemiah says he's exempt, שרגלים לדבר, sheraglayim ladavar,
the fact that he started getting better substantiates the idea that this
is not due to the original wound, it was not a natural
outcome, and so on. Of course, you would actually think the רגלים
לדבר raglayim ladavar
would
have been the תנא קמא, Tanna Kamma, right? Once you assume that
he did die at the end, so okay, he got a little
better in the middle. Anyway, רבי נחמיה Rebbi Nechemiah says that he
estimates the circumstances are that it was not based on the first
wounding and therefore—or a total result of that first act, and therefore
the person is exempt.
So the רגלים לדבר raglayim ladavar the way he's using it means
it's רגלים raglayim to the most recent state of his condition, which
is improving.
I guess so. All right. Okay, tomorrow we will do our last
דף on מסכת נזיר. masechet Nazir.
Coffee drinkers, there's a brand-name surcharge
today. $2
for—and service charge, delivery charge.
That's
for—not for me. 'Cause I'm the one who buys the coffee the
rest of the time, all right? I guess so, yeah.
Sit down here like this? Thank you. I think maybe we should
put the גמרא back.
Yeah, let's put the גמרא'ס Gemara's back up there. And now we
have to—I have to see if this just—as
רגלים לדבר? raglayim ladavar?
The classic?
Yeah, the iconic Dr.
Pepper music... Yeah, okay. It's a good setup down here,
isn't it?
Yeah,
the only problem is, yeah, I need a laptop. This refuses to
do it on my iPhone. The גמרא over there on top of
the—the shelf over there?
No, it would be great, but the iPhone somehow the apps don't
work to do it.
It should work.
I mean maybe if I had a different type of a broadcast
thing going. Oh, I think I'm still doing it.